<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN" "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd">

<chapter id="intro" revision="1">
  <title>Introduction</title>

  <sect1>
    <title>Background</title>

    <para>
      Querydsl was born out of the need to maintain HQL queries in a typesafe way.
      Incremental construction of HQL queries requires String concatenation and results
      in hard to read code. Unsafe references to domain types and properties
      via plain Strings were another issue with String based HQL construction.
    </para>

    <para>
      With a changing domain model type-safety brings huge benefits in software
      development. Domain changes are directly reflected in queries and autocomplete in
      query construction makes query construction faster and safer.
    </para>

    <para>
      HQL for Hibernate was the first target language for Querydsl, but nowadays it
      supports JPA, JDO, JDBC, Lucene, Hibernate Search, MongoDB, Collections and RDFBean
      as backends.
    </para>

  </sect1>

  <sect1>

    <title>Principles</title>

    <para>
      <emphasis>Type safety</emphasis>
      is the core principle of Querydsl. Queries are constructed based on generated query
      types that reflect the properties of your domain types. Also function/method
      invocations are constructed in a fully type-safe manner.
    </para>

    <para>
      <emphasis>Consistency</emphasis>
      is another important principle. The query paths and operations are the same
      in all implementations and also the Query interfaces have a common base interface.
    </para>

    <para>
      All query instances can be reused multiple times. After the projection the paging data
      (limit and offset) and the definition of the projection are removed.
    </para>

    <para>
      To get an impression of the expressivity of the Querydsl query and expression types go to
      the javadocs and explore <code>com.querydsl.Query</code>, <code>com.querydsl.Projectable</code>
      and <code>com.querydsl.core.types.Expression</code>.
    </para>

  </sect1>

</chapter>